Guide to the William Vernon Brelsford Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Vernon Brelsford papers
1891-1974
MS 1642
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, printed material, maps, and photographs relating to Northern Rhodesia (now Zambia) and Nyasaland (now Malawi). Compiled by William Vernon Brelsford.
Brelsford, William Vernon, 1907-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were acquired from Joan W. Banks, 1990 and 1993.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
William Vernon Brelsford was born in 1907 and educated at Oxford. He entered the colonial service in Northern Rhodesia (now Zambia) in 1930. He was named secretary-curator to establish the Rhodes-Livingstone Institute and Museum, 1937-1938; was acting information officer, 1945; acting director of Information, 1948; president of the Northern Rhodesia Society; editor of the Northern Rhodesia Journal, 1950-1965; director of Information, 1951; and director of the Federal Information Department, Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, 1953-1960; and a member of the legislative assembly, 1962-1965. He is the author of many books on Northern Rhodesia.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, printed material, maps, and photographs relating to Northern Rhodesia (now Zambia) and Nyasaland (now Malawi). Compiled by William Vernon Brelsford.
Malawi; Rhodesia and Nyasaland; Zambia; Brelsford, William Vernon, 1907-
- Inventory
  - African Chiefs Course: notes on lectures, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - African dances and songs, 1947-1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Banyama, 1925-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bell, Angus, 1951-1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cannons and guns: correspondence, photograph, 1951-1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cemeteries and graves, 1938, 1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Early History of the Post Office in North-Western Rhodesia," Post Office Magazine, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Feira District, 1948-1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gwembe Valley, 1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Maps, charts, 1898-1902, 1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Memoirs of a District Commissioner of Northern Rhodesia"; Parts 3-5, 1924-1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - North-Eastern/North-Western Rhodesia: volume of administrators' reports, 1892-1902 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Northern Province Development Team/Northern Province Newsletter, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Northern Rhodesia Society/ Northern Rhodesia Journal, 1950-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 15 - 19)
  - Northern Rhodesia/Zambia: reports on marshes, swaps, 1949-1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Notes, jottings, 1909, 1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Official provincial administration data, 1945-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Photographs
    - Northern Rhodesia/Zambia, 1905-1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Northern Rhodesia/Zambia, 1904-1918, 1927, 1949-1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Northern Rhodesia/Zambia, 1914-1929, 1944, 1956, 1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Northern Rhodesia/Zambia, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Nyasaland/Malawi, 1948, 1959, n.d (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Unidentified, 1952, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Police/constabulary shields and uniforms, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Printed material, 1894, 1954, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Psychoanalysis of the native: correspondence with J. F. Ritchie, 1943-1944, 1949, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Radio broadcast transcripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Rhodes-Livingstone Institute, 14th conference, 1960 February (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Writings by William V. Brelsford
    - Some Elephants Die: (A Naturalist and Hunter in Northern Rhodesia), [1947?] (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Articles, reports, 1959-1960, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Articles, reports [most likely written by W. V. B.], 1939, 1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Writings of others
    - "Bibliography of the Kaonde and the Kasempa District," by D. Jaeger, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - "History of Kasempa District (1875-1975)," by D. Jaeger, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Reports, articles, 1891-1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 39 - 40)